It's time for our first LM experiment at this point.
この時点で最初のLM実験の時間だ｡
So some of this you may know well, you may know very well already.
だから､ この中のいくつかはよくご存じかもしれないし､ すでによくご存じかもしれない｡
For some people this might be new, but let me just explain.
初耳の人もいるかもしれないが､ 説明しよう｡
The models that we're going to be using.
これから使うモデルだ｡
These frontier models have been trained in a particular way.
これらのフロンティアモデルは､ 特定の方法で訓練されている｡
That means that they expect two different types of instruction from us the user.
つまり､ 私たちユーザーから2つの異なるタイプの指示を期待されているのだ｡
One of them is known as the system prompt, and one of them is known as the user prompt.
そのうちの1つはシステムプロンプトとして知られ､ もう1つはユーザープロンプトとして知られている｡
The system prompt is something which explains the context of this conversation.
システム・プロンプトは､ この会話の背景を説明するものだ｡
It tells them what kind of task they're performing, what tone they should use, and we'll be experimenting
このコースでは､ システムプロンプトを変更することの意味や､
with what it means to to change a system prompt and what kind of information that you can include in
システムプロンプトにどのような情報を含めることができるかを試していきます｡
The user prompt is the actual conversation itself.
ユーザー・プロンプトは実際の会話そのものである｡
And in our case right now, it's going to just be the the conversation starter.
そして､ 今の私たちの場合は､ 会話のきっかけになるだけだ｡
And the role of the LM of the large language model is to figure out what is the most likely way that
そして､ 大規模な言語モデルのLMの役割は､ このユーザーからのプロンプトが与えられたときに､ 最も可能性の高い応答方法は何かを見つけ出すことである｡
If it's given this user prompt, and in the context of this system prompt, what is the most likely
このユーザー・プロンプトが与えられたとしたら､ そしてこのシステム・プロンプトの文脈の中で､ その次に来る可能性の高いテキストは何だろうか？
That would come from an assistant responding to this user.
それは､ このユーザーに対応するアシスタントのものだろう｡
So that's the difference between the system prompt that sets the context, the user prompt that is the
これが､ 文脈を設定するシステム・プロンプトと､ 会話のきっかけとなるユーザー・プロンプトの違いだ｡
So we're going to set a system prompt.
そこで､ システム・プロンプトを設定する｡
And this is what it's going to say.
そして､ こう書いてある｡
It's going to say you are an assistant that analyzes the contents of a website and provides a short
あなたがウェブサイトのコンテンツを分析し､ ナビゲーションに関連しそうなテキストを無視して短い要約を提供するアシスタントであると言うことになる｡
Respond in markdown.
マークダウンで対応する｡
You'll see more of what that means in in just a second.
それが何を意味するかは､ すぐにわかるだろう｡
So that is our system prompt for the user prompt.
これがユーザー・プロンプトのシステム・プロンプトだ｡
It's going to take as a we're going to write a function user prompt for.
ユーザー・プロンプトの関数を書きます｡
And it's going to take a website as the argument to the function.
そして､ 関数の引数としてウェブサイトを受け取る｡
And it's going to say you are looking at a website titled The Website.
そして､ 「ウェブサイト」というタイトルのウェブサイトを見ていると表示される｡
The contents of this website is as follows.
本ウェブサイトの内容は以下の通りです｡
Please provide a short summary of the website in markdown if it includes news or announcements.
ニュースやお知らせが含まれる場合は､ ウェブサイトの簡単な概要をマークダウンでご記入ください｡
Summarize these two and we then take the text from the website object that Beautifulsoup plucked out
この2つを要約し､ Beautifulsoupが取り出してくれたウェブサイトオブジェクトからテキストを取り出し､
for us, and we add that into the user prompt and we return that user prompt.
それをユーザープロンプトに追加して､ ユーザープロンプトを返す｡
So let's just quickly let's run that cell right now and let's just have a look now.
では､ さっそくこのセルを動かして見てみましょう｡
So after doing that, if I just look at what system Prompt has.
そうして､ プロンプトのシステム構成を見てみよう｡
It has that text of course that we just said.
もちろん､ 今言ったような文章もある｡
And now if you remember earlier on we created a new website object and we stored it in this variable
さて､ 先ほど新しいウェブサイト・オブジェクトを作成し､ この変数エディタに格納したのを覚えているだろうか｡
So if I come here I should be able to say user prompt for and then pass in the object Ed.
だから､ ここに来れば､ ユーザー・プロンプトと言い､ オブジェクト・エドを渡すことができるはずだ｡
And what we'll get is a prompt.
そして､ プロンプトが表示される｡
It might be easier if I print this so that it prints out empty lines.
空行を出力するように印刷すれば簡単かもしれない｡
And here is the user prompt string that we've created.
そしてこれが､ 作成したユーザー・プロンプト文字列である｡
It says you're looking at a website titled blah blah blah.
あなたが見ているのは､ "blah blah blah "というタイトルのウェブサイトです｡
The contents of this website is as follows.
本ウェブサイトの内容は以下の通りです｡
Please provide a short summary.
簡単な要約をお願いします｡
Look, it looks like we should have a space right here, otherwise it might be confusing.
ほら､ ここにスペースがあったほうがよさそうだ｡ そうしないと混乱するかもしれない｡
Let's try that again.
もう一度やってみよう｡
That's always why it's worth printing things as you go, because you'll spot little inconsistencies
そのような小さな矛盾を見つけることができるからだ｡
I think it'll be nicer, actually, now that I look at that.
実際､ 今見ると､ もっと素敵になると思うよ｡
If we have a carriage return there like so.
このようにキャリッジ・リターンがあるとする｡
Let's have a look at this prompt.
このプロンプトを見てみよう｡
Now you're looking at the website and there we go on a separate line that looks good okay.
今､ あなたはウェブサイトを見ている｡
So let's talk about the messages object.
では､ メッセージ・オブジェクトについて話そう｡
So OpenAI expects to receive a conversation in a particular format.
だからOpenAIは､ 特定のフォーマットで会話を受け取ることを期待している｡
It's a format that OpenAI came up with and they used for their APIs, and it became so well used that
これはOpenAIが考え出したフォーマットで､
all of the other major frontier models decided to adopt the same convention.
彼らのAPIに使われている｡
So this has gone from being originally OpenAI's way of using the API to being something of a standard
つまり､ これはもともとOpenAIのAPIの使用方法だったのが､ このアプローチを使用する多くの異なるモデルにおける標準のようなものになったということだ｡
And here's how it works.
その仕組みはこうだ｡
When you're trying to describe a conversation, you describe it using a list a Python list of dictionaries.
会話を記述しようとするとき､ Pythonの辞書のリストを使って記述する｡
So it's a list where each element in the list is a dictionary.
つまり､ リストの各要素が辞書であるリストだ｡
And that dictionary looks like this.
その辞書はこうなっている｡
It's a dictionary with two elements.
これは2つの要素を持つ辞書である｡
One of them has a key of role, and here the value is either system or user, a key of role.
そのうちの1つはroleのキーを持ち､ ここではroleのキーであるsystemかuserのどちらかの値である｡
And the value is system a key of content.
そして､ その価値はコンテンツのキーとなるシステムである｡
And the value is of course the system message.
そして､ その値はもちろんシステム・メッセージである｡
There's another Dictionary where there's a key of role.
もうひとつ､ 役割のカギを握る辞書がある｡
The value is user because it's the user message.
ユーザーメッセージなので､ 値はuserである｡
The user prompt content is where the user message goes.
ユーザープロンプトコンテンツは､ ユーザメッセージが入る場所である｡
User message and user prompt are the same thing.
ユーザーメッセージとユーザープロンプトは同じものです｡
So hopefully I didn't explain it very well, but it makes sense when you see it visually like this.
だから､ うまく説明できなかったかもしれないが､ こうして視覚的に見れば理解できるだろう｡
It's just a dictionary which has role and content, system and system, message user and the user message.
これは､ ロールとコンテンツ､ システムとシステム､ メッセージ・ユーザーとユーザー・メッセージを持つ辞書に過ぎない｡
And there are some other roles as well, but we're going to get to them in good time.
他にもいくつか役割があるが､ それは追って説明する｡
This is all we need for now.
今はこれで十分だ｡
So this is how messages are built.
これがメッセージの作り方だ｡
And if you look at this next function def messages for hopefully it's super clear to you that this is
そして､ この次の関数のdefメッセージを見てもらえば､ これが作成されていることが一目瞭然だろう｡
This here is creating exactly this construct using code.
これは､ まさにこの構造をコードを使って作っている｡
It's going to do it's going to put in there the generic system prompt we came up with.
私たちが考えた一般的なシステムプロンプトを入れるんだ｡
And it's going to create the user prompt for the website.
そして､ ウェブサイトのユーザー・プロンプトを作成する｡
So let's run that.
では､ それを実行してみよう｡
And now, presumably it's clear that if I say messages for Ed, which is the object for my website,
そして今､ 私のウェブサイトのオブジェクトであるEdへのメッセージと言えば､ 空行などが見えるように印刷することは明らかだろう｡
Actually, sorry, in this case it might be better if we don't print it.
実は､ 申し訳ないが､ この場合は印刷しない方がいいかもしれない｡
If we just do this, it might look a bit clearer.
こうすれば､ 少しはスッキリするかもしれない｡
There we go.
これでよし｡
And now you can see that it is it's a list of two things role system.
そして今､ それが2つの役割システムのリストであることがわかるだろう｡
And there's a system message role user.
そして､ システムメッセージの役割ユーザーがいる｡
And there is the user message.
そして､ そこにユーザーメッセージがある｡
Okay.
オーケー｡
It's time to bring this together.
これをまとめる時が来た｡
It's time to actually do it.
今こそ実際にやるときだ｡
The API for OpenAI to make a call to a frontier model to do this for us is super simple, and we're
OpenAIのAPIはとてもシンプルで､ フロンティアモデルを呼び出してこれをやってくれる｡
So whereas now it might look like it's a few things to remember.
だから､ 今は覚えておくべきことがいくつかあるように見えるかもしれない｡
You're going to get so used to this, but we're going to make a function called summarize.
すぐに慣れるだろうが､ これからsummarizeという関数を作る｡
And that is that's going to do the business that's going to solve our problem and summarize a URL that's
そしてそれは､ 私たちの問題を解決し､ 渡されたURLを要約するビジネスを行うことだ｡
It will first create a website for that URL, just like we did for editor.
エディターの時と同じように､ まずそのURLのウェブサイトを作成する｡
And this is where we call OpenAI.
そこでOpenAIと呼んでいる｡
We say OpenAI, which is the the OpenAI object.
OpenAIとは､ OpenAIのオブジェクトのことだ｡
We created OpenAI dot chat, dot completions, dot create.
我々はOpenAIのドットチャット､ ドットコンプリート､ ドットクリエイトを作った｡
And that for now you can just learn it by rote.
そして､ 今はただ暗記すればいいということだ｡
We'll understand a lot more about that later.
そのことについては､ 後でいろいろと理解できるだろう｡
But as far as OpenAI is concerned, this is known as the completions API because we're asking it to
しかし､ OpenAIに関する限り､ これは補完APIとして知られている｡ なぜなら､ この会話を完成させ､
complete this conversation, predict what would be most likely to come next.
次に何が来る可能性が最も高いかを予測するよう求めているからだ｡
We pass in the name of the model we're going to use.
使用するモデルの名前を渡す｡
We're going to use a model called GPT four mini that you'll get very familiar with.
GPT4ミニと呼ばれるモデルを使う｡
It is the light, cheap version of GPT four, the the one of the finest models on the planet, and this
地球上で最高級モデルのひとつであるGPT 4の軽量・廉価版であり､ これを使うには1セントもかからない｡
This, um, you pass in the model and then you pass in the messages and the messages we pass in, use
モデルを渡して､ それからメッセージを渡す｡ メッセージは､
this structure that we've just created and that is all it takes.
今作ったこの構造体を使う｡
What comes back we put in this this object response.
戻ってきたものをこのオブジェクト・レスポンスに入れる｡
And when we get back the response we call response dot choices zero dot message dot content.
そしてレスポンスが返ってきたら､ レスポンス・ドット・チョイス・ゼロ・ドット・メッセージ・ドット・コンテンツと呼ぶ｡
Now I'm going to explain what this is another day we don't need to know.
さて､ これが何なのか､ 私たちが知る必要のない別の日に説明しよう｡
For now.
今のところはね｡
We just need to know that we're going to do response dot choices zero dot message dot content.
あとは､ レスポンス・ドット・チョイス・ゼロ・ドット・メッセージ・ドット・コンテンツを実行することだけだ｡
That's going to be it.
それでいいんだ｡
That is our summarize function.
これが要約機能だ｡
And with that let's try summarizing my website we're running.
ということで､ 私たちが運営しているウェブサイトを要約してみよう｡
It's now connecting to OpenAI in the cloud.
現在はクラウド上のOpenAIに接続している｡
It's making the call and back.
往復するんだ｡
Here is a summary of my website.
以下は私のウェブサイトの要約である｡
We have just uh, spent a fraction of a cent and we have just summarized my website.
ほんのわずかなお金を使い､ 私のウェブサイトを要約した｡
We can do a little bit better because we can print this in a nice style.
私たちは､ これを素敵なスタイルで印刷することができるので､ 少し良いことができます｡
Uh, GPT four, we've asked to respond in markdown, and that means that it's responded with various
ええと､ GPT4はマークダウンで回答するようお願いしました｡ つまり､ 見出しや太字のものなど､
characters to represent headings, things in bold and so on.
さまざまな文字を使って回答しているということです｡
And we can use a feature of Jupyter Labs that we can ask it to actually show that in a nice markdown
Jupyter Labsの機能を使って､ マークダウン形式で表示させることもできる｡
So let's do that.
だから､ そうしよう｡
Let's use this display summary function and try again.
この要約表示機能を使って､ もう一度やってみよう｡
Again we're going to GPT for a mini in the cloud.
今回もクラウド上のミニをGPTにする｡
And here is a summary of my website.
そして､ これが私のウェブサイトの要約である｡
Uh, it says something about me.
ええと､ 僕について何か書いてある｡
Uh, and it's uh yeah, very nicely formatted, very nicely structured.
とてもきれいなフォーマットで､ とてもきれいに構成されている｡
Pretty impressive.
かなり印象的だ｡
And apparently it highlights my work with proprietary LMS, offers resources related to AI and LMS,
そしてどうやら､ 私が独自に開発したLMSでの仕事にハイライトを当て､ AIとLMSに関連するリソースを提供し､
showcasing his commitment to advancing knowledge in this field.
この分野での知識の発展に尽力していることをアピールしているようだ｡
Good for you, GPT for mini.
よかったね､ ミニのGPT｡
That's a very nice summary.
とてもいいまとめだ｡
Okay.
オーケー｡
And now we can try some more websites.
そして今､ さらにいくつかのウェブサイトを試すことができる｡
Let's try summarizing cnn.com.
CNNを要約してみよう｡  comに移籍した｡
Uh, we'll see what this happens.
まあ､ どうなるか見てみよう｡
Obviously, CNN is a much bigger, uh, result you've got here.
CNNの方がはるかに大きな結果を出しているのは明らかだ｡
Uh, and, uh, we get some information about what's going on.
それで､ 何が起こっているのか､ いくつかの情報を得ることができた｡
I'm actually recording this right now on the 5th of November at, uh, in the evening, which is the
実は今､ 11月5日の夕方にこれを録音しているんですが､ これは今行われている2024年の選挙の日なんです｡
So that, of course, is featured on CNN's web page.
もちろん､ それはCNNのウェブページで紹介されている｡
We can also summarize anthropic, which is the website for Claude.
クロードのウェブサイトである "アントロピック "を要約することもできる｡
And they have a nice page.
素敵なページもある｡
And here you go.
さあ､ どうぞ
And you can read more about it in this nice little summary of their web page.
その詳細については､ 彼らのウェブページのこの素敵な要約をご覧いただきたい｡
All right.
分かった｡
And that wraps up our first instant gratification.
これで､ 最初のインスタント・グラティフィケーションは終了だ｡
It's it's juicy.
ジューシーだ｡
It's something where we've actually done something useful.
実際に役に立つことをしたんだ｡
We've scraped the web.
我々はウェブをスクラップした｡
We've summarized summarization is one of the most common AI use cases.
要約は最も一般的なAIの使用例の一つである｡
So common it's useful for all sorts of purposes.
一般的なものなので､ あらゆる用途に使える｡
We'll be doing it a few different ways during during this course, even in our week eight a sticky solution
このコースの間､ いくつかの異なる方法でそれを行う予定だが､ 8週目の粘着ソリューションでも､
will be using something that will do some summarization.
要約を行うものを使う予定だ｡
So it's a great, uh, thing to have experimented with already.
だから､ すでに実験していることは素晴らしいことなんだ｡
So there are so many other business applications of summarization.
だから､ 要約のビジネスへの応用は他にもたくさんある｡
This is something you should be able to put to good use.
これは有効活用できるはずだ｡
You should be able to think of some ways you could apply this to your day job right away, or be building
すぐにでも自分の仕事に応用できる方法を思いついたり､ GitHubで要約の実例となるプロジェクトをいくつか作ったりできるはずだ｡
You could apply it to summarizing the news, summarizing financial performance from a financial report,
ニュースの要約､ 財務報告書からの業績の要約､ 履歴書､ カバーレターなどに応用できるだろう｡
You could you could take a resume and generate a cover letter.
履歴書からカバーレターを作成することもできる｡
Uh, there are so many different things you can do with summarization of of documents.
ドキュメントの要約でできることはたくさんある｡
And also adding on to that the scraping the web angle of it.
それに加えて､ ウェブのスクレイピングという側面もある｡
So have a think about how you would apply summarization to your business and try extending this to do
だから､ あなたのビジネスに要約をどのように適用するか考え､ これを拡張して要約をしてみてほしい｡
There's also uh, for for the more technically inclined, uh, one of the things that you'll discover
また､ 技術志向の人向けには､ この方法を使うとすぐにわかることがある｡ それは､
quite quickly when you use this is that there are many websites that cannot be summarized with this
この方法では要約できないウェブサイトがたくさんあるということで､ それはウェブページのレンダリングにJavaScriptを使っていて､
approach, and that's because they use JavaScript to render the web page and are rather simplistic.
かなり単純化しているからだ｡
Approach has just taken the the just just made the requests the server call and taken what we get back.
アプローチは､ ただサーバーにリクエストして､ 返ってきたものを受け取っただけだ｡
But there's a solution.
しかし､ 解決策はある｡
And the solution is to use a platform like selenium or others like it, or playwright, which would
解決策としては､ セレニウムなどのプラットフォームや､ playwrightを使えば､ ページをレンダリングして､
allow you to render the page and and do it that way.
そのように実行することができる｡
So if you're technically inclined and have some background with that kind of thing, then a really interesting
だから､ もしあなたが技術的な傾向があり､ そのようなことについてのバックグラウンドがあるのなら､
challenge is to turn this into something that's a bit beefier and add selenium to the mix.
本当に興味深い挑戦は､ これをもう少しビーフなものに変えて､ セレンをミックスに加えることだ｡
Um, as it happens, someone has already done that.
うーん､ 偶然にも､ 誰かがすでにそれをやっている｡
Uh, one of the students, thank you very much.
ええと､ 生徒の一人です､ ありがとうございました｡
And if you go into this folder community contributions, you'll see a few different solutions.
そして､ このフォルダーのコミュニティへの貢献を見てみると､ いくつかの異なる解決策がある｡
And one of them is a selenium based solution.
そのひとつがセレンベースのソリューションだ｡
So you can always go in and just just look at that yourself.
だから､ いつでも中に入って自分で見ることができる｡
Or you can have a shot at doing it too.
あるいは､ あなたにもチャンスがある｡
And you'll find the solution in there.
そこに解決策があるはずだ｡
And if you do come up with a solution to that or to anything, I would love it if you were willing to
そして､ もしあなたがその解決策や何かを思いついたなら､ 他の人がその恩恵を受けられるようにコードを共有してくれると嬉しい｡
Ideally, put it in the community contributions folder and be sure to clear the output.
理想的なのは､ それをコミュニティへの貢献フォルダに入れ､ 出力をクリアすることだ｡
So you go to kernel restart kernel and clear outputs of all cells.
そこでカーネルを再起動し､ すべてのセルの出力をクリアする｡
Otherwise, everything that you've got in your output would also get checked into code which which would
そうしないと､ 出力されたものすべてがコードにチェックされることになる｡
So so do that.
だから､ そうしてくれ｡
And then if you could submit a PR, a pull request, I can then merge that into the code.
そして､ PR（プル・リクエスト）を提出してもらえれば､ それをコードにマージすることができる｡
And if that's a new thing for you, it is a bit of a process.
そして､ それがあなたにとって初めてのことであるなら､ それはちょっとしたプロセスなのだ｡
There is a write up here for exactly what you need to do to make that work.
そのために必要なことは､ ここに書いてある｡
Anyways, this was the first project, the first of many.
とにかく､ これが最初のプロジェクトで､ 多くのプロジェクトの最初のものだった｡
It's a simple project, but it's an important one.
シンプルなプロジェクトだが､ 重要なものだ｡
A very important business use case.
非常に重要なビジネスユースケースだ｡
I hope you found it worthwhile.
有意義なものであったことを願っている｡
I will see you for the next video when we wrap up.
また次のビデオでお会いしましょう｡
Week one.
週目｡
Day one.
初日｡